’t	O	O	O	O	O
Lopt	O	O	O	O	O
tegen	O	O	O	O	O
d’	O	O	O	O	O
aovend	O	O	O	O	O
van	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
mooie	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
zunnege	O	O	O	O	O
Septemberdag	B-MISC	B-MISC	B-MISC	B-MISC	B-MISC
.	O	O	O	O	O
Zoo	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
dag	O	O	O	O	O
is	O	O	O	O	O
geld	O	O	O	O	O
weerd	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
te	O	O	O	O	O
minsen	O	O	O	O	O
veur	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
man	O	O	O	O	O
van	O	O	O	O	O
dat	O	O	O	O	O
groote	O	O	O	O	O
florisante	O	O	O	O	O
boerenhoes	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dat	O	O	O	O	O
daor	O	O	O	O	O
achter	O	O	O	O	O
dei	O	O	O	O	O
breide	O	O	O	O	O
grafte	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
schârrege	O	O	O	O	O
lindeboomen	O	O	O	O	O
ligt	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
Is	O	O	O	O	O
ein	O	O	O	O	O
van	O	O	O	O	O
dei	O	O	O	O	O
groote	O	O	O	O	O
boerenplaotsen	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
zooas	O	O	O	O	O
ze	O	O	O	O	O
d’r	O	O	O	O	O
tegenwoordig	O	O	O	O	O
zoo	O	O	O	O	O
veul	O	O	O	O	O
bin	O	O	O	O	O
in	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	B-LOC
Oldambt	B-LOC	B-LOC	B-LOC	B-LOC	I-LOC
.	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
Heim	O	O	O	B-LOC	O
is	O	O	O	O	O
roem	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
mooi	O	O	O	O	O
ânlegd	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
lânge	O	O	O	O	O
opridlaone	O	O	O	O	O
gait	O	O	O	O	O
achter	O	O	O	O	O
nao	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
groote	O	O	O	O	O
schure	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
hoes	O	O	O	O	O
zulf	O	O	O	O	O
springt	O	O	O	O	O
ân	O	O	O	O	O
weêrskanten	O	O	O	O	O
mit	O	O	O	O	O
twei	O	O	O	O	O
of	O	O	O	O	O
drei	O	O	O	O	O
smâlle	O	O	O	O	O
vensters	O	O	O	O	O
oet	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Dizze	O	O	O	O	O
plaotse	O	O	O	O	O
hier	O	O	O	O	O
heurt	O	O	O	O	O
an	O	O	O	O	O
Jân	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
Robbers	I-PER	I-PER	I-PER	I-PER	I-PER
,	O	O	O	O	O
ein	O	O	O	O	O
van	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
riekste	O	O	O	O	O
boeren	O	O	O	O	O
van	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
loug	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Hij	O	O	O	O	O
is	O	O	O	O	O
al	O	O	O	O	O
tien	O	O	O	O	O
jaor	O	O	O	O	O
wedeman	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
zien	O	O	O	O	O
olste	O	O	O	O	O
dochter	O	O	O	O	O
Trudao	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
,	O	O	O	O	O
dei	O	O	O	O	O
nō	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
hoeshollen	O	O	O	O	O
dut	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
is	O	O	O	O	O
einentwintig	O	O	O	O	O
jaor	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Zien	O	O	O	O	O
baide	O	O	O	O	O
ânder	O	O	O	O	O
kinder	O	O	O	O	O
bin	O	O	O	O	O
veul	O	O	O	O	O
jonger	O	O	O	O	O
;	O	O	O	O	O
d’r	O	O	O	O	O
bin	O	O	O	O	O
twei	O	O	O	O	O
tusschen	O	O	O	O	O
dood	O	O	O	O	O
in	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
mezzels	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Jantje	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
,	O	O	O	O	O
dei	O	O	O	O	O
op	O	O	O	O	O
Trudao	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
volgt	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
is	O	O	O	O	O
nō	O	O	O	O	O
zestien	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
veur	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
jaor	O	O	O	O	O
nao	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
stad	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Lammert	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
,	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
jongste	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
is	O	O	O	O	O
elf	O	O	O	O	O
jaor	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
gait	O	O	O	O	O
nog	O	O	O	O	O
nao	O	O	O	O	O
schoule	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Op	O	O	O	O	O
dit	O	O	O	O	O
oogenblik	O	O	O	O	O
net	O	O	O	O	O
stait	O	O	O	O	O
boer	O	O	O	O	O
Robbers	B-PER	B-PER	O	B-PER	B-PER
op	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
laone	O	O	O	O	O
te	O	O	O	O	O
praoten	O	O	O	O	O
mit	O	O	O	O	O
ein	O	O	O	O	O
van	O	O	O	O	O
zien	O	O	O	O	O
naobers	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Robbers	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
is	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
forsche	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dreige	O	O	O	O	O
kerel	O	O	O	O	O
mit	O	O	O	O	O
donker	O	O	O	O	O
haor	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
oogen	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
vol	O	O	O	O	O
rood	O	O	O	O	O
gezichte	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
kört	O	O	O	O	O
schoren	O	O	O	O	O
baord	O	O	O	O	O
;	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
man	O	O	O	O	O
nog	O	O	O	O	O
in	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
volle	O	O	O	O	O
kracht	O	O	O	O	O
van	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
leven	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
even	O	O	O	O	O
in	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
vieftig	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Nō	O	O	O	O	O
’e	O	O	O	O	O
net	O	O	O	O	O
ofschaid	O	O	O	O	O
nemt	O	O	O	O	O
van	O	O	O	O	O
zien	O	O	O	O	O
naober	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
achter	O	O	O	O	O
nao	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
schure	O	O	O	O	O
gait	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
waor	O	O	O	O	O
ze	O	O	O	O	O
drok	O	O	O	O	O
an	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
inhaolen	O	O	O	O	O
bin	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
kikt	O	O	O	O	O
’e	O	O	O	O	O
neit	O	O	O	O	O
zoo	O	O	O	O	O
heil	O	O	O	O	O
vrundelk	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Waorom	O	O	O	O	O
toch	O	O	O	O	O
?	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
hâr	O	O	O	O	O
jah	O	O	O	O	O
zoo	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
beste	O	O	O	O	O
dag	O	O	O	O	O
wêst	O	O	O	O	O
van	O	O	O	O	O
daoge	O	O	O	O	O
!	O	O	O	O	O
Mit	O	O	O	O	O
veir	O	O	O	O	O
span	O	O	O	O	O
hârren	O	O	O	O	O
ze	O	O	O	O	O
an	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
mennen	O	O	O	O	O
west	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
al	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
wit	O	O	O	O	O
koren	O	O	O	O	O
was	O	O	O	O	O
mooi	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
dreuge	O	O	O	O	O
bie	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
ander	O	O	O	O	O
komen	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Dat	O	O	O	O	O
was	O	O	O	O	O
hom	O	O	O	O	O
wat	O	O	O	O	O
weerd	O	O	O	O	O
;	O	O	O	O	O
hij	O	O	O	O	O
hâr	O	O	O	O	O
zoo’n	O	O	O	O	O
groot	O	O	O	O	O
gebroek	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
duchtige	O	O	O	O	O
lappe	O	O	O	O	O
lând	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
wat	O	O	O	O	O
vōl	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
koren	O	O	O	O	O
tou	O	O	O	O	O
in	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
schudden	O	O	O	O	O
!	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
Arbaidsvolk	O	B-MISC	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dat	O	O	O	O	O
zōk	O	O	O	O	O
zoo	O	O	O	O	O
fiks	O	O	O	O	O
weerd	O	O	O	O	O
hâr	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
begript	O	O	O	O	O
neit	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
waorom	O	O	O	O	O
Robbers	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
zoo	O	O	O	O	O
nusterig	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
grammietig	O	O	O	O	O
is	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Dèn	O	O	O	O	O
râgt	O	O	O	O	O
’e	O	O	O	O	O
op	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
knecht	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dei	O	O	O	O	O
in	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
vankgat	O	O	O	O	O
stait	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dèn	O	O	O	O	O
dut	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
vleier	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
hōm	O	O	O	O	O
verkeerd	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
stoppeljong	O	O	O	O	O
dei	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
waogenhârken	O	O	O	O	O
dee	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
kricht	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
draaier	O	O	O	O	O
om	O	O	O	O	O
d’	O	O	O	O	O
ooren	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
omdat	O	O	O	O	O
’e	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
paor	O	O	O	O	O
aoren	O	O	O	O	O
liggen	O	O	O	O	O
laoten	O	O	O	O	O
het	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Pollo	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
wōs	O	O	O	O	O
ook	O	O	O	O	O
neit	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
wat	O	O	O	O	O
’e	O	O	O	O	O
d’r	O	O	O	O	O
an	O	O	O	O	O
hâr	O	O	O	O	O
;	O	O	O	O	O
hij	O	O	O	O	O
lôpt	O	O	O	O	O
zien	O	O	O	O	O
baos	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dei	O	O	O	O	O
âns	O	O	O	O	O
nog	O	O	O	O	O
al	O	O	O	O	O
mâl	O	O	O	O	O
mit	O	O	O	O	O
hōm	O	O	O	O	O
is	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
eebn	O	O	O	O	O
veur	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
vouten	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
kricht	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
schop	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dat	O	O	O	O	O
’e	O	O	O	O	O
hoelend	O	O	O	O	O
wegstōft	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Berend	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
,	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
vaste	O	O	O	O	O
arbaider	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dei	O	O	O	O	O
vraogen	O	O	O	O	O
wôl	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
of	O	O	O	O	O
’e	O	O	O	O	O
zöndag	O	O	O	O	O
peerd	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
kōrrewaogen	O	O	O	O	O
kriegen	O	O	O	O	O
kan	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
om	O	O	O	O	O
nao	O	O	O	O	O
zien	O	O	O	O	O
vraus	O	O	O	O	O
ollen	O	O	O	O	O
te	O	O	O	O	O
gaon	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
denkt	O	O	O	O	O
bie	O	O	O	O	O
zōk	O	O	O	O	O
zulf	O	O	O	O	O
:	O	O	O	O	O
“	O	O	O	O	O
doe	O	O	O	O	O
hôlst	O	O	O	O	O
die	O	O	O	O	O
stil	O	O	O	O	O
Berend	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
,	O	O	O	O	O
van	O	O	O	O	O
daoge	O	O	O	O	O
;	O	O	O	O	O
dien	O	O	O	O	O
boer	O	O	O	O	O
stait	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
mutse	O	O	O	O	O
neit	O	O	O	O	O
goud	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
”	O	O	O	O	O
Robbers	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
was	O	O	O	O	O
eeb’n	O	O	O	O	O
nao	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
ânder	O	O	O	O	O
ênne	O	O	O	O	O
van	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
schure	O	O	O	O	O
loopen	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
“	O	O	O	O	O
Ik	O	O	O	O	O
kon	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
neit	O	O	O	O	O
helpen	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
”	O	O	O	O	O
jeuzelt	O	O	O	O	O
Lubbert	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
,	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
stoppeljong	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dei	O	O	O	O	O
neit	O	O	O	O	O
recht	O	O	O	O	O
wies	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
maor	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
doodgoude	O	O	O	O	O
slokkert	O	O	O	O	O
is	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
“	O	O	O	O	O
ik	O	O	O	O	O
kon	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
neit	O	O	O	O	O
hêlpen	O	O	O	O	O
;	O	O	O	O	O
d’r	O	O	O	O	O
bin	O	O	O	O	O
drei	O	O	O	O	O
tannen	O	O	O	O	O
oet	O	O	O	O	O
mien	O	O	O	O	O
harke	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
”	O	O	O	O	O
Peiter	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
,	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
dârde	O	O	O	O	O
knecht	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dei	O	O	O	O	O
vaok	O	O	O	O	O
veur	O	O	O	O	O
Lubbert	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
opkwâm	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
maor	O	O	O	O	O
hom	O	O	O	O	O
nog	O	O	O	O	O
vaoker	O	O	O	O	O
in	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
ootje	O	O	O	O	O
nam	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
kricht	O	O	O	O	O
nō	O	O	O	O	O
medelieden	O	O	O	O	O
mit	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
vent	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Hol	O	O	O	O	O
die	O	O	O	O	O
maor	O	O	O	O	O
stille	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
mien	O	O	O	O	O
jong	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
zee	O	O	O	O	O
’e	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
zet	O	O	O	O	O
hom	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
pette	O	O	O	O	O
wat	O	O	O	O	O
t’rechte	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
zelt	O	O	O	O	O
zöndag	O	O	O	O	O
mien	O	O	O	O	O
tebaksdeuze	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
daor	O	O	O	O	O
Nepooljon	O	B-PER	O	B-PER	B-PER
op	O	O	O	O	O
stait	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
in	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
buutse	O	O	O	O	O
hebben	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
’k	O	O	O	O	O
heb	O	O	O	O	O
ook	O	O	O	O	O
nog	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
halfpeeriesder	O	O	O	O	O
veur	O	O	O	O	O
die	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Heinrich	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
,	O	O	O	O	O
d’	O	O	O	O	O
Oostvreize	O	O	O	B-LOC	B-LOC
knecht	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dei	O	O	O	O	O
in	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
vankgat	O	O	O	O	O
stait	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
van	O	O	O	O	O
Diele	B-LOC	B-LOC	B-LOC	B-LOC	B-LOC
van	O	O	O	O	O
daon	O	O	O	O	O
is	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
zegt	O	O	O	O	O
:	O	O	O	O	O
noe	O	O	O	O	O
kömt	O	O	O	O	O
oenglük	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
zooveul	O	O	O	O	O
zègen	O	O	O	O	O
mit	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
eernte	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
oen	O	O	O	O	O
noe	O	O	O	O	O
nog	O	O	O	O	O
zoo	O	O	O	O	O
stoensk	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dat	O	O	O	O	O
lidt	O	O	O	O	O
Mareie	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
nich	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Bie	O	O	O	O	O
oens	O	O	O	O	O
in	O	O	O	O	O
Diele	B-LOC	B-LOC	B-LOC	B-LOC	B-LOC
is	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
maol	O	O	O	O	O
gebeurd	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Pak	O	O	O	O	O
dei	O	O	O	O	O
schove	O	O	O	O	O
ân	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
Heinrich	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
,	O	O	O	O	O
zegt	O	O	O	O	O
Berend	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
,	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
vertel	O	O	O	O	O
ons	O	O	O	O	O
dat	O	O	O	O	O
daols	O	O	O	O	O
nao	O	O	O	O	O
holdert	O	O	O	O	O
Heinrich	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
mog	O	O	O	O	O
geern	O	O	O	O	O
wat	O	O	O	O	O
laaiern	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
wat	O	O	O	O	O
leigen	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
hâr	O	O	O	O	O
altied	O	O	O	O	O
lange	O	O	O	O	O
verhaolen	O	O	O	O	O
van	O	O	O	O	O
âlderhande	O	O	O	O	O
veurteikens	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
meraokels	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
maor	O	O	O	O	O
waor	O	O	O	O	O
gein	O	O	O	O	O
mens	O	O	O	O	O
wat	O	O	O	O	O
van	O	O	O	O	O
leufde	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Maor	O	O	O	O	O
waorom	O	O	O	O	O
was	O	O	O	O	O
Robbers	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
zoo	O	O	O	O	O
nusterig	O	O	O	O	O
?	O	O	O	O	O
Veldhoes	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
,	O	O	O	O	O
zien	O	O	O	O	O
naober	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
hâr	O	O	O	O	O
hom	O	O	O	O	O
wat	O	O	O	O	O
vertêld	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
wat	O	O	O	O	O
hom	O	O	O	O	O
lang	O	O	O	O	O
neit	O	O	O	O	O
ânston	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Veldhoes	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
was	O	O	O	O	O
wat	O	O	O	O	O
ofgunstig	O	O	O	O	O
op	O	O	O	O	O
Robbers	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
en	O	O	O	O	O
hâr	O	O	O	O	O
daorin	O	O	O	O	O
ook	O	O	O	O	O
neit	O	O	O	O	O
âlle	O	O	O	O	O
schuld	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Veldhoes	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
zat	O	O	O	O	O
op	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
huurplaotse	O	O	O	O	O
mit	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
hoes	O	O	O	O	O
vōl	O	O	O	O	O
groote	O	O	O	O	O
kinder	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dei	O	O	O	O	O
’e	O	O	O	O	O
neit	O	O	O	O	O
ân	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
gang	O	O	O	O	O
helpen	O	O	O	O	O
kon	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Robbers	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
leit	O	O	O	O	O
hom	O	O	O	O	O
gedurig	O	O	O	O	O
vuilen	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dat	O	O	O	O	O
zien	O	O	O	O	O
ōlste	O	O	O	O	O
zeun	O	O	O	O	O
d’r	O	O	O	O	O
al	O	O	O	O	O
twei	O	O	O	O	O
winters	O	O	O	O	O
mit	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
beugelseeze	O	O	O	O	O
op	O	O	O	O	O
oet	O	O	O	O	O
west	O	O	O	O	O
hâr	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
maor	O	O	O	O	O
neit	O	O	O	O	O
ânraoken	O	O	O	O	O
kon	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
alderdeegs	O	O	O	O	O
neit	O	O	O	O	O
bie	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
wedevrau	O	O	O	O	O
met	O	O	O	O	O
kinder	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Hij	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
rieke	O	O	O	O	O
Robbers	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
,	O	O	O	O	O
kon	O	O	O	O	O
zien	O	O	O	O	O
kinder	O	O	O	O	O
elk	O	O	O	O	O
wel	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
plaotse	O	O	O	O	O
geven	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
as't	O	O	O	O	O
’r	O	O	O	O	O
op	O	O	O	O	O
ânkwam	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Dat	O	O	O	O	O
stak	O	O	O	O	O
Veldhoes	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
;	O	O	O	O	O
maor	O	O	O	O	O
nō	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
nō	O	O	O	O	O
wōs	O	O	O	O	O
’e	O	O	O	O	O
wat	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
waor	O	O	O	O	O
’e	O	O	O	O	O
Robbers	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
ook	O	O	O	O	O
ais	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
loer	O	O	O	O	O
mit	O	O	O	O	O
draaien	O	O	O	O	O
kon	O	O	O	O	O
!	O	O	O	O	O
Nao	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
boodschapke	O	O	O	O	O
over	O	O	O	O	O
zaaikoren	O	O	O	O	O
begunde	O	O	O	O	O
hij	O	O	O	O	O
al	O	O	O	O	O
gauw	O	O	O	O	O
:	O	O	O	O	O
Welzoo	O	O	O	O	O
naober	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
nō	O	O	O	O	O
krieg	O	O	O	O	O
ie	O	O	O	O	O
van	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
winter	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
vrijer	O	O	O	O	O
ook	O	O	O	O	O
in	O	O	O	O	O
hoes	O	O	O	O	O
?	O	O	O	O	O
Ie	O	O	O	O	O
raoken	O	O	O	O	O
joen	O	O	O	O	O
ōlste	O	O	O	O	O
dochter	O	O	O	O	O
den	O	O	O	O	O
wel	O	O	O	O	O
gauw	O	O	O	O	O
kwiet	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Robbers	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
keek	O	O	O	O	O
hom	O	O	O	O	O
verwonderd	O	O	O	O	O
ân	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
wōs	O	O	O	O	O
neit	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
wat	O	O	O	O	O
’e	O	O	O	O	O
daoroet	O	O	O	O	O
verstaon	O	O	O	O	O
mōs	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Wat	O	O	O	O	O
mân	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
wat	O	O	O	O	O
zeg	O	O	O	O	O
ie	O	O	O	O	O
?	O	O	O	O	O
Trudao	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
de	O	O	O	O	O
vrijer	O	O	O	O	O
?	O	O	O	O	O
hou	O	O	O	O	O
koom	O	O	O	O	O
ie	O	O	O	O	O
daor	O	O	O	O	O
in	O	O	O	O	O
vredesnaom	O	O	O	O	O
bie	O	O	O	O	O
!	O	O	O	O	O
Nō	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
jah	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dat	O	O	O	O	O
zōl	O	O	O	O	O
ie	O	O	O	O	O
neit	O	O	O	O	O
weiten	O	O	O	O	O
;	O	O	O	O	O
dat	O	O	O	O	O
wil	O	O	O	O	O
’k	O	O	O	O	O
ook	O	O	O	O	O
wel	O	O	O	O	O
leuven	O	O	O	O	O
!	O	O	O	O	O
Maor	O	O	O	O	O
man	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
wat	O	O	O	O	O
mein	O	O	O	O	O
ie	O	O	O	O	O
wel	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
hôl	O	O	O	O	O
je	O	O	O	O	O
mie	O	O	O	O	O
veur	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
gek	O	O	O	O	O
?	O	O	O	O	O
onz’	O	O	O	O	O
Trudao	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
?	O	O	O	O	O
Dênken	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
lu	O	O	O	O	O
d’r	O	O	O	O	O
misschein	O	O	O	O	O
weer	O	O	O	O	O
wat	O	O	O	O	O
oet	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
omdat	O	O	O	O	O
ze	O	O	B-PER	O	O
neit	O	O	O	O	O
nao	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
achtentwintigsten	B-MISC	B-MISC	B-MISC	O	B-MISC
Augustus	I-MISC	I-MISC	I-MISC	B-MISC	I-MISC
wêst	O	O	O	O	O
het	O	O	O	O	O
?	O	O	O	O	O
Meinen	O	O	O	O	O
ze	O	O	O	O	O
den	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dat	O	O	O	O	O
Klaos	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
Goldland	I-PER	I-PER	I-PER	I-PER	I-PER
’t	O	O	O	O	O
nog	O	O	O	O	O
ais	O	O	O	O	O
weêr	O	O	O	O	O
perbeirt	O	O	O	O	O
het	O	O	O	O	O
?	O	O	O	O	O
Niks	O	O	O	O	O
van	O	O	O	O	O
dat	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
ze	O	O	O	O	O
was	O	O	O	O	O
wat	O	O	O	O	O
kepot	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
ze	O	O	O	O	O
hâr	O	O	O	O	O
daogs	O	O	O	O	O
van	O	O	O	O	O
te	O	O	O	O	O
veuren	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
koorse	O	O	O	O	O
had	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
bleef	O	O	O	O	O
daorom	O	O	O	O	O
in	O	O	O	O	O
hoes	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Maor	O	O	O	O	O
man	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
’k	O	O	O	O	O
wōl	O	O	O	O	O
joe	O	O	O	O	O
loozer	O	O	O	O	O
hebben	O	O	O	O	O
;	O	O	O	O	O
ie	O	O	O	O	O
zōllen	O	O	O	O	O
neit	O	O	O	O	O
weiten	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
wat	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
heile	O	O	O	O	O
dörp	O	O	O	O	O
weit	O	O	O	O	O
?	O	O	O	O	O
Of	O	O	O	O	O
bin	O	O	O	O	O
ie	O	O	O	O	O
den	O	O	O	O	O
werachtig	O	O	O	O	O
zoo	O	O	O	O	O
onneuzel	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dat	O	O	O	O	O
ie	O	O	O	O	O
joe	O	O	O	O	O
van	O	O	O	O	O
joen	O	O	O	O	O
aigen	O	O	O	O	O
dochter	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
rad	O	O	O	O	O
veur	O	O	O	O	O
d’	O	O	O	O	O
oogen	O	O	O	O	O
draaien	O	O	O	O	O
laoten	O	O	O	O	O
?	O	O	O	O	O
Kepot	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
jàh	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
flaitpiepen	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
kepot	O	O	O	O	O
!	O	O	O	O	O
ze	O	O	O	O	O
hâr	O	O	O	O	O
al	O	O	O	O	O
lânk	O	O	O	O	O
mit	O	O	O	O	O
Albert	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
Korenhof	I-PER	I-PER	I-PER	I-PER	I-PER
ofsproken	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dat	O	O	O	O	O
’e	O	O	O	O	O
dei	O	O	O	O	O
middag	O	O	O	O	O
komen	O	O	O	O	O
zōl	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Vaoder	O	O	O	O	O
was	O	O	O	O	O
nao	O	O	O	O	O
’n	B-LOC	B-LOC	B-LOC	B-LOC	B-LOC
Dam	I-LOC	I-LOC	I-LOC	I-LOC	I-LOC
,	O	O	O	O	O
Kepot	O	O	O	O	O
!	O	O	O	O	O
gouje	O	O	O	O	O
mörgen	O	O	O	O	O
;	O	O	O	O	O
Kepot	O	O	O	O	O
!	O	O	O	O	O
ie	O	O	O	O	O
weiten	O	O	O	O	O
doch	O	O	O	O	O
ook	O	O	O	O	O
wel	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dat	O	O	O	O	O
’e	O	O	O	O	O
heur	O	O	O	O	O
têls	O	O	O	O	O
altied	O	O	O	O	O
nao	O	O	O	O	O
hoes	O	O	O	O	O
brengt	O	O	O	O	O
;	O	O	O	O	O
in	O	O	O	O	O
doomnies	O	O	O	O	O
hoes	O	O	O	O	O
komen	O	O	O	O	O
ze	O	O	O	O	O
bie	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
ander	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
lêst	O	O	O	O	O
op	O	O	O	O	O
Damster	O	B-LOC	B-LOC	B-ORG	B-LOC
riederij	O	O	O	I-ORG	O
nō	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
ie	O	O	O	O	O
zōllen	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
neit	O	O	O	O	O
weiten	O	O	O	O	O
!	O	O	O	O	O
Leugens	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
al	O	O	O	O	O
leugens	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
zee	O	O	O	O	O
Robbers	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
niedig	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
beet	O	O	O	O	O
zōk	O	O	O	O	O
op	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
lippen	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Nō	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
zegt	O	O	O	O	O
Veldhoes	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
,	O	O	O	O	O
wil	O	O	O	O	O
ie	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
den	O	O	O	O	O
volstrekt	O	O	O	O	O
gein	O	O	O	O	O
woord	O	O	O	O	O
hebben	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dan	O	O	O	O	O
mout	O	O	O	O	O
ie	O	O	O	O	O
ook	O	O	O	O	O
maor	O	O	O	O	O
oppazzen	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dat	O	O	O	O	O
Albert	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
neit	O	O	O	O	O
op	O	O	O	O	O
klaorlichten	O	O	O	O	O
dag	O	O	O	O	O
bie	O	O	O	O	O
joe	O	O	O	O	O
komt	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
as	O	O	O	O	O
Trudao	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
allênne	O	O	O	O	O
in	O	O	O	O	O
hoes	O	O	O	O	O
is	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
eerst	O	O	O	O	O
weer	O	O	O	O	O
weg	O	O	O	O	O
gait	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
as	O	O	O	O	O
’e	O	O	O	O	O
joe	O	O	O	O	O
mit	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
peerd	O	O	O	O	O
achter	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
hoes	O	O	O	O	O
komen	O	O	O	O	O
heurt	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Zoo	O	O	O	O	O
was	O	O	O	O	O
Veldhoes	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
weg	O	O	O	O	O
gaon	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
Robbers	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
bleef	O	O	O	O	O
in	O	O	O	O	O
ein	O	O	O	O	O
stōk	O	O	O	O	O
staon	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Hij	O	O	O	O	O
wōl	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
neit	O	O	O	O	O
leuven	O	O	O	O	O
;	O	O	O	O	O
nee	O	O	O	O	O
!	O	O	O	O	O
nee	O	O	O	O	O
!	O	O	O	O	O
dat	O	O	O	O	O
was	O	O	O	O	O
neit	O	O	O	O	O
waor	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dat	O	O	O	O	O
kon	O	O	O	O	O
neit	O	O	O	O	O
!	O	O	O	O	O
En	O	O	O	O	O
dat	O	O	O	O	O
alles	O	O	O	O	O
zōl	O	O	O	O	O
boeten	O	O	O	O	O
hōm	O	O	O	O	O
omgaon	O	O	O	O	O
wezen	O	O	O	O	O
?	O	O	O	O	O
Onmeugelk	O	O	O	O	O
!	O	O	O	O	O
doch	O	O	O	O	O
!	O	O	O	O	O
doch	O	O	O	O	O
!	O	O	O	O	O
hou	O	O	O	O	O
langer	O	O	O	O	O
of	O	O	O	O	O
’e	O	O	O	O	O
d’r	O	O	O	O	O
over	O	O	O	O	O
dôcht	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
hou	O	O	O	O	O
meer	O	O	O	O	O
dingen	O	O	O	O	O
hōm	O	O	O	O	O
in	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
zin	O	O	O	O	O
kwammen	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
daor	O	O	O	O	O
’e	O	O	O	O	O
eerst	O	O	O	O	O
niks	O	O	O	O	O
gein	O	O	O	O	O
ârg	O	O	O	O	O
in	O	O	O	O	O
had	O	O	O	O	O
hâr	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Trudao	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
,	O	O	O	O	O
dat	O	O	O	O	O
wōs	O	O	O	O	O
’e	O	O	O	O	O
wel	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
kwam	O	O	O	O	O
vaok	O	O	O	O	O
bie	O	O	O	O	O
doomnies	O	O	O	O	O
Lize	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
,	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
Albert	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
was	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
groot	O	O	O	O	O
vrund	O	O	O	O	O
van	O	O	O	O	O
August	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
,	O	O	O	O	O
doomnie	O	O	O	O	O
zien	O	O	O	O	O
zeun	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dei	O	O	O	O	O
op	O	O	O	O	O
studie	O	O	O	O	O
was	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
maor	O	O	O	O	O
Nō	O	O	O	O	O
al	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
heil	O	O	O	O	O
zet	O	O	O	O	O
in	O	O	O	O	O
hoes	O	O	O	O	O
wêst	O	O	O	O	O
hâr	O	O	O	O	O
mit	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
vekansie	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
En	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
jao	O	O	O	O	O
!	O	O	O	O	O
as	O	O	O	O	O
’e	O	O	O	O	O
zōk	O	O	O	O	O
bedocht	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dou	O	O	O	O	O
’e	O	O	O	O	O
lêst	O	O	O	O	O
van	O	O	O	O	O
’n	B-LOC	B-LOC	B-LOC	B-LOC	B-LOC
Dam	I-LOC	I-LOC	I-LOC	I-LOC	I-LOC
in	O	O	O	O	O
hoes	O	O	O	O	O
komen	O	O	O	O	O
was	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dou	O	O	O	O	O
hâr	O	O	O	O	O
’e	O	O	O	O	O
neit	O	O	O	O	O
âns	O	O	O	O	O
verwacht	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
as	O	O	O	O	O
dat	O	O	O	O	O
Trudao	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
al	O	O	O	O	O
lânk	O	O	O	O	O
op	O	O	O	O	O
bère	O	O	O	O	O
legen	O	O	O	O	O
hâr	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
omdat	O	O	O	O	O
ze	O	O	O	O	O
wat	O	O	O	O	O
mieterig	O	O	O	O	O
was	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
ze	O	O	O	O	O
hâr	O	O	O	O	O
nog	O	O	O	O	O
opzeten	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
ânkled	O	O	O	O	O
wêst	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
al	O	O	O	O	O
!	O	O	O	O	O
Wel	O	O	O	O	O
verdraaid	O	O	O	O	O
!	O	O	O	O	O
as	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
eis	O	O	O	O	O
waor	O	O	O	O	O
was	O	O	O	O	O
?	O	O	O	O	O
Dei	O	O	O	O	O
beroerde	O	O	O	O	O
kaoljaoger	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
zeun	O	O	O	O	O
van	O	O	O	O	O
dei	O	O	O	O	O
groothâns	O	O	O	O	O
!	O	O	O	O	O
Zien	O	O	O	O	O
dochter	O	O	O	O	O
zōk	O	O	O	O	O
ophollen	O	O	O	O	O
met	O	O	O	O	O
eine	O	O	O	O	O
oet	O	O	O	O	O
zoo	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
rötterge	O	O	O	O	O
boudel	O	O	O	O	O
?	O	O	O	O	O
Maor	O	O	O	O	O
nee	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
nee	O	O	O	O	O
!	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
wazzen	O	O	O	O	O
leugens	O	O	O	O	O
!	O	O	O	O	O
Veldhoes	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
mog	O	O	O	O	O
geern	O	O	O	O	O
wat	O	O	O	O	O
steukeln	O	O	O	O	O
!	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
Was	O	O	O	O	O
jah	O	O	O	O	O
te	O	O	O	O	O
gek	O	O	O	O	O
!	O	O	O	O	O
Vleden	O	O	O	O	O
winter	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dat	O	O	O	O	O
wōs	O	O	O	O	O
’e	O	O	O	O	O
wel	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
hâr	O	O	O	O	O
ze	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
maol	O	O	O	O	O
mit	O	O	O	O	O
hōm	O	O	O	O	O
wêst	O	O	O	O	O
op	O	O	O	O	O
scheuvels	O	O	O	O	O
;	O	O	O	O	O
maor	O	O	O	O	O
kiek	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
op	O	O	O	O	O
scheuvels	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dat	O	O	O	O	O
ken	O	O	O	O	O
je	O	O	O	O	O
altied	O	O	O	O	O
zoo	O	O	O	O	O
net	O	O	O	O	O
neit	O	O	O	O	O
hebben	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Maor	O	O	O	O	O
âns	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
leek	O	O	O	O	O
jah	O	O	O	O	O
niks	O	O	O	O	O
!	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
cent	O	O	O	O	O
bie	O	O	O	O	O
heur	O	O	O	O	O
gulden	O	O	O	O	O
!	O	O	O	O	O
Zóó	O	O	O	O	O
zōl	O	O	O	O	O
ze	O	O	O	O	O
zōk	O	O	O	O	O
neit	O	O	O	O	O
versmieten	O	O	O	O	O
!	O	O	O	O	O
En	O	O	O	O	O
mog	O	O	O	O	O
ze	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
in	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
hârsens	O	O	O	O	O
kriegen	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
n	O	O	O	O	O
o	O	O	O	O	O
o	O	O	O	O	O
i	O	O	O	O	O
t	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
n	O	O	O	O	O
o	O	O	O	O	O
o	O	O	O	O	O
i	O	O	O	O	O
t	O	O	O	O	O
wil	O	O	O	O	O
’k	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
lieden	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
kaoljaoger	O	O	O	O	O
komt	O	O	O	O	O
mie	O	O	O	O	O
neit	O	O	O	O	O
weer	O	O	O	O	O
over	O	O	O	O	O
deure	O	O	O	O	O
of	O	O	O	O	O
druppel	O	O	O	O	O
!	O	O	O	O	O
Zoo	O	O	O	O	O
om	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
bie	O	O	O	O	O
wazzen	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
gedachten	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dei	O	O	O	O	O
Robbers	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
deur	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
kop	O	O	O	O	O
gongen	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
hij	O	O	O	O	O
wōs	O	O	O	O	O
van	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
veurige	O	O	O	O	O
winter	O	O	O	O	O
nog	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dat	O	O	O	O	O
hij	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
zien	O	O	O	O	O
dochter	O	O	O	O	O
in	O	O	O	O	O
zōkke	O	O	O	O	O
zaoken	O	O	O	O	O
neit	O	O	O	O	O
geliek	O	O	O	O	O
dochten	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
dat	O	O	O	O	O
Trudao	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
van	O	O	O	O	O
vōlhollen	O	O	O	O	O
wōs	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
hou	O	O	O	O	O
zacht	O	O	O	O	O
of	O	O	O	O	O
ze	O	O	O	O	O
ook	O	O	O	O	O
leek	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
Was	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dou	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
einigste	O	O	O	O	O
zeun	O	O	O	O	O
van	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
rieke	O	O	O	O	O
Jan	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
Goldland	I-PER	I-PER	I-PER	I-PER	I-PER
’t	O	O	O	O	O
om	O	O	O	O	O
heur	O	O	O	O	O
ândeinen	O	O	O	O	O
laoten	O	O	O	O	O
hâr	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
Was	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
schatrieke	O	O	O	O	O
jong	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dei	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
mooie	O	O	O	O	O
plaotse	O	O	O	O	O
hâr	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
pak	O	O	O	O	O
geld	O	O	O	O	O
d’r	O	O	O	O	O
boven	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
ook	O	O	O	O	O
nog	O	O	O	O	O
al	O	O	O	O	O
van	O	O	O	O	O
zien	O	O	O	O	O
muike	O	O	O	O	O
ârven	O	O	O	O	O
kon	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Robbers	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
hâr	O	O	O	O	O
d’r	O	O	O	O	O
hârd	O	O	O	O	O
veur	O	O	O	O	O
wêst	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
maor	O	O	O	O	O
Trudao	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
wōl	O	O	O	O	O
nârgens	O	O	O	O	O
van	O	O	O	O	O
heuren	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
As	O	O	O	O	O
Robbers	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
heur	O	O	O	O	O
veurrekende	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
hou	O	O	O	O	O
riek	O	O	O	O	O
of	O	O	O	O	O
Goldland	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
wel	O	O	O	O	O
wōr	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
zee	O	O	O	O	O
ze	O	O	O	O	O
einvaudig	O	O	O	O	O
:	O	O	O	O	O
dout	O	O	O	O	O
maor	O	O	O	O	O
gein	O	O	O	O	O
muite	O	O	O	O	O
vaoder	O	O	O	O	O
;	O	O	O	O	O
ie	O	O	O	O	O
maggen	O	O	O	O	O
praoten	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
wat	O	O	O	O	O
ie	O	O	O	O	O
willen	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
’k	O	O	O	O	O
neem	O	O	O	O	O
hōm	O	O	O	O	O
neit	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
’k	O	O	O	O	O
Mag	O	O	O	O	O
hōm	O	O	O	O	O
neit	O	O	O	O	O
lieden	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
of	O	O	O	O	O
’e	O	O	O	O	O
mie	O	O	O	O	O
lieden	O	O	O	O	O
mag	O	O	O	O	O
of	O	O	O	O	O
neit	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
’k	O	O	O	O	O
weit	O	O	O	O	O
d’r	O	O	O	O	O
ook	O	O	O	O	O
niks	O	O	O	O	O
van	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Einmaol	O	O	O	O	O
van	O	O	O	O	O
mien	O	O	O	O	O
leven	O	O	O	O	O
heb	O	O	O	O	O
’k	O	O	O	O	O
hōm	O	O	O	O	O
even	O	O	O	O	O
sproken	O	O	O	O	O
;	O	O	O	O	O
hij	O	O	O	O	O
komt	O	O	O	O	O
d’r	O	O	O	O	O
maor	O	O	O	O	O
zoo	O	O	O	O	O
op	O	O	O	O	O
ôf	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Ik	O	O	O	O	O
weit	O	O	O	O	O
wel	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
gait	O	O	O	O	O
veul	O	O	O	O	O
meer	O	O	O	O	O
zoo	O	O	O	O	O
onder	O	O	O	O	O
onze	O	O	O	O	O
stând	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
maor	O	O	O	O	O
wat	O	O	O	O	O
gevolgen	O	O	O	O	O
zei	O	O	O	O	O
je	O	O	O	O	O
d’r	O	O	O	O	O
alsmis	O	O	O	O	O
ook	O	O	O	O	O
van	O	O	O	O	O
?	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
Is	O	O	O	O	O
luk	O	O	O	O	O
of	O	O	O	O	O
raok	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
as	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
goud	O	O	O	O	O
gait	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Dat	O	O	O	O	O
altied	O	O	O	O	O
snârren	O	O	O	O	O
van	O	O	O	O	O
zien	O	O	O	O	O
geld	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
riekdom	O	O	O	O	O
stait	O	O	O	O	O
mie	O	O	O	O	O
ook	O	O	O	O	O
tegen	O	O	O	O	O
;	O	O	O	O	O
we	O	O	O	O	O
pazzen	O	O	O	O	O
niks	O	O	O	O	O
bie	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
ander	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
âs	O	O	O	O	O
’e	O	O	O	O	O
nō	O	O	O	O	O
Vrijdag	B-MISC	B-MISC	B-MISC	B-MISC	B-MISC
weer	O	O	O	O	O
komt	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
zeg	O	O	O	O	O
’k	O	O	O	O	O
hōm	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
of	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
zunder	O	O	O	O	O
âns	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Hou	O	O	O	O	O
Robbers	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
’t	O	O	O	O	O
ook	O	O	O	O	O
muide	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
hij	O	O	O	O	O
kon	O	O	O	O	O
d’r	O	O	O	O	O
niks	O	O	O	O	O
ân	O	O	O	O	O
doun	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Trudao	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
gong	O	O	O	O	O
heur	O	O	O	O	O
gâng	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
hij	O	O	O	O	O
troostte	O	O	O	O	O
zōk	O	O	O	O	O
in	O	O	O	O	O
stilte	O	O	O	O	O
mit	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
gedachte	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dat	O	O	O	O	O
ze	O	O	O	O	O
nog	O	O	O	O	O
wel	O	O	O	O	O
eis	O	O	O	O	O
weer	O	O	O	O	O
verzuik	O	O	O	O	O
kriegen	O	O	O	O	O
zōl	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dat	O	O	O	O	O
net	O	O	O	O	O
zoo	O	O	O	O	O
goud	O	O	O	O	O
was	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Net	O	O	O	O	O
zoo	O	O	O	O	O
goud	O	O	O	O	O
?	O	O	O	O	O
Nee	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
d’r	O	O	O	O	O
wazzen	O	O	O	O	O
meer	O	O	O	O	O
jongs	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dei	O	O	O	O	O
zien	O	O	O	O	O
dochter	O	O	O	O	O
liek	O	O	O	O	O
doun	O	O	O	O	O
konnen	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
maor	O	O	O	O	O
zoo	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
rieke	O	O	O	O	O
brommer	O	O	O	O	O
as	O	O	O	O	O
Klaos	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
Goldlând	I-PER	I-PER	I-PER	I-PER	I-PER
was	O	O	O	O	O
d’r	O	O	O	O	O
neit	O	O	O	O	O
meer	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Doch	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
hij	O	O	O	O	O
kon	O	O	O	O	O
mit	O	O	O	O	O
Trudao	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
niks	O	O	O	O	O
ânvangen	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
ze	O	O	O	O	O
docht	O	O	O	O	O
net	O	O	O	O	O
as	O	O	O	O	O
heur	O	O	O	O	O
Moetje	O	O	O	O	O
!	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
Lêste	O	O	O	O	O
vour	O	O	O	O	O
was	O	O	O	O	O
binnen	O	O	O	O	O
;	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
begunde	O	O	O	O	O
al	O	O	O	O	O
wat	O	O	O	O	O
te	O	O	O	O	O
dauwen	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
donker	O	O	O	O	O
te	O	O	O	O	O
worren	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
Volk	O	O	O	O	O
was	O	O	O	O	O
bliede	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dat	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
holdert	O	O	O	O	O
was	O	O	O	O	O
;	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
hâr	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
dikke	O	O	O	O	O
dag	O	O	O	O	O
wêst	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
ze	O	O	O	O	O
kregen	O	O	O	O	O
zin	O	O	O	O	O
an	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
maol	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Wat	O	O	O	O	O
is	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
geploeter	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
gewaske	O	O	O	O	O
daor	O	O	O	O	O
bie	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
pompe	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
wat	O	O	O	O	O
dut	O	O	O	O	O
dei	O	O	O	O	O
eine	O	O	O	O	O
blauwe	O	O	O	O	O
handdouk	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
deinsten	O	O	O	O	O
!	O	O	O	O	O
Frisch	O	O	B-PER	O	O
zein	O	O	O	O	O
ze	O	O	O	O	O
d’r	O	O	O	O	O
oet	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dei	O	O	O	O	O
knechten	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
dei	O	O	O	O	O
ârbaiders	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
nō	O	O	O	O	O
ze	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
oogenblik	O	O	O	O	O
laoter	O	O	O	O	O
bie	O	O	O	O	O
taofel	O	O	O	O	O
zitten	O	O	O	O	O
mit	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
viefschaften	O	O	O	O	O
overscheiters	O	O	O	O	O
ân	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Dei	O	O	O	O	O
overscheiters	O	O	O	O	O
mit	O	O	O	O	O
witte	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
roode	O	O	O	O	O
opslaogen	O	O	O	O	O
;	O	O	O	O	O
doomnies	O	O	O	O	O
August	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
zee	O	O	O	O	O
d’r	O	O	O	O	O
van	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dat	O	O	O	O	O
ze	O	O	O	O	O
k	O	O	O	O	O
l	O	O	O	O	O
a	O	O	O	O	O
s	O	O	O	O	O
s	O	O	O	O	O
i	O	O	O	O	O
e	O	O	O	O	O
k	O	O	O	O	O
wazzen	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Wat	O	O	O	O	O
dat	O	O	O	O	O
bedudde	O	O	O	O	O
wōssen	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
lu	O	O	O	O	O
in	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
dörp	O	O	O	O	O
nō	O	O	O	O	O
wel	O	O	O	O	O
neit	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
maor	O	O	O	O	O
d’	O	O	O	O	O
ôlsten	O	O	O	O	O
mōg	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
neit	O	O	O	O	O
heugen	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dat	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
slag	O	O	O	O	O
van	O	O	O	O	O
dei	O	O	O	O	O
overscheiters	O	O	O	O	O
ooit	O	O	O	O	O
âns	O	O	O	O	O
worren	O	O	O	O	O
was	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Koopman	O	O	O	O	O
Krans	B-PER	B-PER	I-PER	B-PER	B-PER
,	O	O	O	O	O
dei	O	O	O	O	O
over	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
teunbanke	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
snedig	O	O	O	O	O
woordje	O	O	O	O	O
zeggen	O	O	O	O	O
kon	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
hoes	O	O	O	O	O
vol	O	O	O	O	O
dochters	O	O	O	O	O
hâr	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
zee	O	O	O	O	O
vaok	O	O	O	O	O
:	O	O	O	O	O
as	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
mode	O	O	O	O	O
zoo	O	O	O	O	O
min	O	O	O	O	O
invloud	O	O	O	O	O
hâr	O	O	O	O	O
op	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
kleir	O	O	O	O	O
van	O	O	O	O	O
mien	O	O	O	O	O
dochters	O	O	O	O	O
as	O	O	O	O	O
op	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
overscheiters	O	O	O	O	O
van	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
boerenknechten	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dan	O	O	O	O	O
kon	O	O	O	O	O
d’r	O	O	O	O	O
bie	O	O	O	O	O
mie	O	O	O	O	O
alle	O	O	O	O	O
jaor	O	O	O	O	O
wat	O	O	O	O	O
overscheiten	O	O	O	O	O
;	O	O	O	O	O
nō	O	O	O	O	O
bin	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
wichter	O	O	O	O	O
zooveul	O	O	O	O	O
neudig	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dat	O	O	O	O	O
ik	O	O	O	O	O
d’r	O	O	O	O	O
zulf	O	O	O	O	O
overscheit	O	O	O	O	O
!	O	O	O	O	O
Wat	O	O	O	O	O
dampt	O	O	O	O	O
dei	O	O	O	O	O
brei	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
wat	O	O	O	O	O
hebben	O	O	O	O	O
ze	O	O	O	O	O
d’r	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
zin	O	O	O	O	O
ân	O	O	O	O	O
!	O	O	O	O	O
Eerst	O	O	O	O	O
even	O	O	O	O	O
achter	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
pette	O	O	O	O	O
!	O	O	O	O	O
Vief	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
zes	O	O	O	O	O
tellen	O	O	O	O	O
maor	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
flôp	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
bin	O	O	O	O	O
al	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
petten	O	O	O	O	O
weer	O	O	O	O	O
op	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Boven	O	O	O	O	O
ân	O	O	O	O	O
zit	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
grootknecht	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dei	O	O	O	O	O
ook	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
eerste	O	O	O	O	O
in	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
schuttel	O	O	O	O	O
tast	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Op	O	O	O	O	O
hōm	O	O	O	O	O
volgen	O	O	O	O	O
d’	O	O	O	O	O
andere	O	O	O	O	O
knechten	O	O	O	O	O
mit	O	O	O	O	O
Lubbert	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
,	O	O	O	O	O
dan	O	O	O	O	O
Berend	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
de	O	O	O	O	O
vaste	O	O	O	O	O
ârbaider	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
dèn	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
andere	O	O	O	O	O
ârbaiders	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Wat	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
gelach	O	O	O	O	O
gait	O	O	O	O	O
d’r	O	O	O	O	O
op	O	O	O	O	O
!	O	O	O	O	O
Peiter	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
het	O	O	O	O	O
oettrokken	O	O	O	O	O
west	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
vertelt	O	O	O	O	O
heur	O	O	O	O	O
van	O	O	O	O	O
Nimwegen	B-LOC	B-LOC	B-LOC	B-PER	B-PER
,	O	O	O	O	O
waor	O	O	O	O	O
’e	O	O	O	O	O
legen	O	O	O	O	O
het	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
Zetje	O	O	O	O	O
hâr	O	O	O	O	O
’e	O	O	O	O	O
nog	O	O	O	O	O
oppasser	O	O	O	O	O
west	O	O	O	O	O
bie	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
knel	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dou	O	O	O	O	O
d’	O	O	O	O	O
ander	O	O	O	O	O
oppasser	O	O	O	O	O
zeik	O	O	O	O	O
was	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Wat	O	O	O	O	O
was	O	O	O	O	O
dat	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
raore	O	O	O	O	O
kerel	O	O	O	O	O
dei	O	O	O	O	O
knel	O	O	O	O	O
!	O	O	O	O	O
As	O	O	O	O	O
Peiter	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
eis	O	O	O	O	O
wat	O	O	O	O	O
verkeird	O	O	O	O	O
daon	O	O	O	O	O
hâr	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
’e	O	O	O	O	O
hōm	O	O	O	O	O
oetraggen	O	O	O	O	O
wōl	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
hâr	O	O	O	O	O
’e	O	O	O	O	O
zegd	O	O	O	O	O
:	O	O	O	O	O
jij	O	O	O	O	O
boer	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
jij	O	O	O	O	O
lompe	O	O	O	O	O
boer	O	O	O	O	O
!	O	O	O	O	O
Nō	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dat	O	O	O	O	O
was	O	O	O	O	O
mooi	O	O	O	O	O
oetraggen	O	O	O	O	O
;	O	O	O	O	O
zóó	O	O	O	O	O
wōllen	O	O	O	O	O
d’	O	O	O	O	O
andern	O	O	O	O	O
ook	O	O	O	O	O
wel	O	O	O	O	O
oetragd	O	O	O	O	O
worren	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
as	O	O	O	O	O
ze	O	O	O	O	O
d’r	O	O	O	O	O
den	O	O	O	O	O
maor	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
boerenplaotse	O	O	O	O	O
mit	O	O	O	O	O
kregen	O	O	O	O	O
!	O	O	O	O	O
En	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
kerel	O	O	O	O	O
hâr	O	O	O	O	O
meind	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dat	O	O	O	O	O
ze	O	O	O	O	O
hier	O	O	O	O	O
in	O	O	O	O	O
Grönnegerland	B-LOC	B-LOC	B-LOC	B-LOC	B-LOC
almaol	O	O	O	O	O
in	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
kaste	O	O	O	O	O
sleipen	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
alle	O	O	O	O	O
daoge	O	O	O	O	O
endelkouke	O	O	O	O	O
atten	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Nō	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dat	O	O	O	O	O
zōl	O	O	O	O	O
wat	O	O	O	O	O
moois	O	O	O	O	O
wezen	O	O	O	O	O
!	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
Eiwege	O	O	O	O	O
domme	O	O	O	O	O
kerel	O	O	O	O	O
hâr	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
wêst	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dei	O	O	O	O	O
k	O	O	O	O	O
n	O	O	O	O	O
e	O	O	O	O	O
l	O	O	O	O	O
!	O	O	O	O	O
Zoo	O	O	O	O	O
heil	O	O	O	O	O
snedig	O	O	O	O	O
of	O	O	O	O	O
fien	O	O	O	O	O
bin	O	O	O	O	O
ze	O	O	O	O	O
juust	O	O	O	O	O
neit	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
grappen	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dei	O	O	O	O	O
d’r	O	O	O	O	O
nog	O	O	O	O	O
meer	O	O	O	O	O
verteld	O	O	O	O	O
worren	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
maor	O	O	O	O	O
smaokelk	O	O	O	O	O
lachen	O	O	O	O	O
ze	O	O	O	O	O
d’r	O	O	O	O	O
doch	O	O	O	O	O
om	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dei	O	O	O	O	O
kerels	O	O	O	O	O
mit	O	O	O	O	O
heur	O	O	O	O	O
breide	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
verbrânde	O	O	O	O	O
gezichten	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
ze	O	O	O	O	O
doun	O	O	O	O	O
zōk	O	O	O	O	O
onderwiel	O	O	O	O	O
duchtig	O	O	O	O	O
te	O	O	O	O	O
goude	O	O	O	O	O
ân	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
brei	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Stil	O	O	O	O	O
is	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
in	O	O	O	O	O
ins	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
doodstil	O	O	O	O	O
!	O	O	O	O	O
Robbers	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
komt	O	O	O	O	O
der	O	O	O	O	O
in	O	O	O	O	O
;	O	O	O	O	O
hij	O	O	O	O	O
het	O	O	O	O	O
zōk	O	O	O	O	O
ân	O	O	O	O	O
ânkled	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
allozie	O	O	O	O	O
mit	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
dikke	O	O	O	O	O
gollen	O	O	O	O	O
kette	O	O	O	O	O
op	O	O	O	O	O
zied	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Hij	O	O	O	O	O
bestelt	O	O	O	O	O
ân	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
grootknecht	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
wat	O	O	O	O	O
d’r	O	O	O	O	O
mörgen	O	O	O	O	O
vroug	O	O	O	O	O
eerst	O	O	O	O	O
gebeuren	O	O	O	O	O
mout	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
vragt	O	O	O	O	O
daorop	O	O	O	O	O
ân	O	O	O	O	O
Rikste	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
,	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
groote	O	O	O	O	O
maid	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dei	O	O	O	O	O
net	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
breikoeme	O	O	O	O	O
weer	O	O	O	O	O
volschept	O	O	O	O	O
:	O	O	O	O	O
waor	O	O	O	O	O
is	O	O	O	O	O
Trudao	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
?	O	O	O	O	O
Trudao	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
zit	O	O	O	O	O
allenn’	O	O	O	O	O
in	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
oetstek	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
is	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
antwoord	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
Was	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
zoo	O	O	O	O	O
as	O	O	O	O	O
Rikste	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
zee	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Trudao	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
zit	O	O	O	O	O
allenn’	O	O	O	O	O
in	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
oetstek	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
zoo	O	O	O	O	O
as	O	O	O	O	O
ein	O	O	O	O	O
van	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
achterste	O	O	O	O	O
kaomers	O	O	O	O	O
nuimt	O	O	O	O	O
wōr	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dei	O	O	O	O	O
mit	O	O	O	O	O
ein	O	O	O	O	O
venster	O	O	O	O	O
oetspringt	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Ze	O	O	O	O	O
het	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
lâmpe	O	O	O	O	O
net	O	O	O	O	O
ânstoken	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
Is	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
nuver	O	O	O	O	O
wicht	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dei	O	O	O	O	O
Trudao	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
,	O	O	O	O	O
zooas	O	O	O	O	O
ze	O	O	O	O	O
daor	O	O	O	O	O
zit	O	O	O	O	O
mit	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
helder	O	O	O	O	O
sangenbont	O	O	O	O	O
mörgenjaske	O	O	O	O	O
ân	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Ze	O	O	O	O	O
hâr	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
drok	O	O	O	O	O
had	O	O	O	O	O
mit	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
zörgen	O	O	O	O	O
veur	O	O	O	O	O
âl	O	O	O	O	O
dat	O	O	O	O	O
volk	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
Is	O	O	O	O	O
ook	O	O	O	O	O
in	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
boonentied	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
vrougriepe	O	O	O	O	O
peren	O	O	O	O	O
mozzen	O	O	O	O	O
ook	O	O	O	O	O
ân	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
zied	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
omdat	O	O	O	O	O
ze	O	O	O	O	O
zoo	O	O	O	O	O
begunden	O	O	O	O	O
te	O	O	O	O	O
rötten	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
Was	O	O	O	O	O
heur	O	O	O	O	O
daorom	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
muite	O	O	O	O	O
neit	O	O	O	O	O
meer	O	O	O	O	O
weerd	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
zōk	O	O	O	O	O
heilendal	O	O	O	O	O
ân	O	O	O	O	O
te	O	O	O	O	O
kleiden	O	O	O	O	O
;	O	O	O	O	O
ze	O	O	O	O	O
trōk	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
schoon	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
helder	O	O	O	O	O
mörgenjaske	O	O	O	O	O
ân	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
zit	O	O	O	O	O
nō	O	O	O	O	O
vlietig	O	O	O	O	O
te	O	O	O	O	O
hoozen	O	O	O	O	O
stoppen	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
Is	O	O	O	O	O
of	O	O	O	O	O
ze	O	O	O	O	O
heur	O	O	O	O	O
Moetje	O	O	O	O	O
oet	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
mond	O	O	O	O	O
sneden	O	O	O	O	O
is	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
zeggen	O	O	O	O	O
all’n	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dei	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
vrau	O	O	O	O	O
van	O	O	O	O	O
Robbers	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
nog	O	O	O	O	O
kend	O	O	O	O	O
hebben	O	O	O	O	O
;	O	O	O	O	O
ze	O	O	O	O	O
het	O	O	O	O	O
net	O	O	O	O	O
dei	O	O	O	O	O
zachte	O	O	O	O	O
oogen	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dei	O	O	O	O	O
fiene	O	O	O	O	O
neuze	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
mond	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
ze	O	O	O	O	O
is	O	O	O	O	O
ook	O	O	O	O	O
zoo	O	O	O	O	O
groot	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
raizig	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
het	O	O	O	O	O
net	O	O	O	O	O
heur	O	O	O	O	O
Moetjes	O	O	O	O	O
gâng	O	O	O	O	O
ook	O	O	O	O	O
!	O	O	O	O	O
Trudao	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
hâr	O	O	O	O	O
ook	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
jaor	O	O	O	O	O
in	O	O	O	O	O
Grönnegen	B-LOC	B-LOC	B-LOC	B-LOC	B-LOC
west	I-LOC	I-LOC	O	I-LOC	I-LOC
,	O	O	O	O	O
net	O	O	O	O	O
as	O	O	O	O	O
Jântje	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
nō	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Dat	O	O	O	O	O
heurt	O	O	O	O	O
d’r	O	O	O	O	O
jah	O	O	O	O	O
tegenwoordig	O	O	O	O	O
zoo	O	O	O	O	O
bie	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
zegt	O	O	O	O	O
Robbers	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
,	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
as	O	O	O	O	O
mien	O	O	O	O	O
kinder	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
neit	O	O	O	O	O
doun	O	O	O	O	O
zellen	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
wêl	O	O	O	O	O
zel	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
den	O	O	O	O	O
doun	O	O	O	O	O
!	O	O	O	O	O
Trudao	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
hâr	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
nao	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
zeggen	O	O	O	O	O
van	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
lu	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
wat	O	O	O	O	O
jufferknepen	O	O	O	O	O
over	O	O	O	O	O
zōk	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Of	O	O	O	O	O
dat	O	O	O	O	O
kwam	O	O	O	O	O
van	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
stad	O	O	O	O	O
of	O	O	O	O	O
van	O	O	O	O	O
heur	O	O	O	O	O
verkeiren	O	O	O	O	O
mit	O	O	O	O	O
doomnies	O	O	O	O	O
Lize	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
,	O	O	O	O	O
─	O	O	O	O	O
ze	O	O	O	O	O
wozzen	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
neit	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
moar	O	O	O	O	O
heur	O	O	O	O	O
hoeshollen	O	O	O	O	O
dee	O	O	O	O	O
ze	O	O	O	O	O
goud	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
heur	O	O	O	O	O
botter	O	O	O	O	O
was	O	O	O	O	O
best	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
maiden	O	O	O	O	O
hollen	O	O	O	O	O
kon	O	O	O	O	O
ze	O	O	O	O	O
beter	O	O	O	O	O
as	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
ânder	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Wat	O	O	O	O	O
was	O	O	O	O	O
ze	O	O	O	O	O
goudgeefs	O	O	O	O	O
veur	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
ârmen	O	O	O	O	O
;	O	O	O	O	O
net	O	O	O	O	O
as	O	O	O	O	O
heur	O	O	O	O	O
Moetje	O	O	O	O	O
!	O	O	O	O	O
Robbers	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
leit	O	O	O	O	O
heur	O	O	O	O	O
daor	O	O	O	O	O
altied	O	O	O	O	O
neit	O	O	O	O	O
zoo	O	O	O	O	O
goud	O	O	O	O	O
in	O	O	O	O	O
geworren	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
as	O	O	O	O	O
in	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
verkeiren	O	O	O	O	O
mit	O	O	O	O	O
doomnies	O	O	O	O	O
Lize	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
.	O	O	O	O	O
Lize	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
was	O	O	O	O	O
wel	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
kaole	O	O	O	O	O
juffer	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
maor	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
was	O	O	O	O	O
toch	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
doomnies	O	O	O	O	O
dochter	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
as	O	O	O	O	O
juffer	O	O	O	O	O
Lize	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
d’r	O	O	O	O	O
was	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dee	O	O	O	O	O
’e	O	O	O	O	O
alderdeegs	O	O	O	O	O
muite	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
om	O	O	O	O	O
wat	O	O	O	O	O
hoogelk	O	O	O	O	O
te	O	O	O	O	O
praoten	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
wat	O	O	O	O	O
hom	O	O	O	O	O
aigentliek	O	O	O	O	O
neit	O	O	O	O	O
heil	O	O	O	O	O
glad	O	O	O	O	O
of	O	O	O	O	O
gong	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Trudao	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
hâr	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
suns	O	O	O	O	O
ze	O	O	O	O	O
Veldhoes	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
bie	O	O	O	O	O
heur	O	O	O	O	O
vaoder	O	O	O	O	O
staon	O	O	O	O	O
zein	O	O	O	O	O
hâr	O	O	O	O	O
te	O	O	O	O	O
praoten	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
al	O	O	O	O	O
neit	O	O	O	O	O
rustig	O	O	O	O	O
west	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Veldhoes	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
was	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
teutert	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dat	O	O	O	O	O
wōs	O	O	O	O	O
ze	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Nō	O	O	O	O	O
heur	O	O	O	O	O
vaoder	O	O	O	O	O
den	O	O	O	O	O
bie	O	O	O	O	O
heur	O	O	O	O	O
in	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
kaomer	O	O	O	O	O
komt	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
deure	O	O	O	O	O
niedig	O	O	O	O	O
achter	O	O	O	O	O
zōk	O	O	O	O	O
dicht	O	O	O	O	O
gooit	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
weit	O	O	O	O	O
ze	O	O	O	O	O
al	O	O	O	O	O
zoowat	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
waor	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
ân	O	O	O	O	O
tou	O	O	O	O	O
is	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
d’	O	O	O	O	O
Oetslag	O	O	O	O	O
van	O	O	O	O	O
Robbers	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
zien	O	O	O	O	O
gedachten	O	O	O	O	O
was	O	O	O	O	O
worren	O	O	O	O	O
:	O	O	O	O	O
van	O	O	O	O	O
aovend	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
van	O	O	O	O	O
aovend	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
as	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
wârk	O	O	O	O	O
ofloopen	O	O	O	O	O
is	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
wil	O	O	O	O	O
’k	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
weiten	O	O	O	O	O
;	O	O	O	O	O
van	O	O	O	O	O
aovend	O	O	O	O	O
zel	O	O	O	O	O
ze	O	O	O	O	O
d’r	O	O	O	O	O
veur	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Hij	O	O	O	O	O
valt	O	O	O	O	O
den	O	O	O	O	O
ook	O	O	O	O	O
vōt	O	O	O	O	O
mit	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
deure	O	O	O	O	O
in	O	O	O	O	O
hoes	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
gait	O	O	O	O	O
mit	O	O	O	O	O
d’	O	O	O	O	O
ârms	O	O	O	O	O
over	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
ander	O	O	O	O	O
liek	O	O	O	O	O
veur	O	O	O	O	O
zien	O	O	O	O	O
dochter	O	O	O	O	O
staon	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
zegt	O	O	O	O	O
:	O	O	O	O	O
Trudao	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
,	O	O	O	O	O
zeg	O	O	O	O	O
mie	O	O	O	O	O
nao	O	O	O	O	O
waorhaid	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
waorom	O	O	O	O	O
wolt	O	O	O	O	O
doe	O	O	O	O	O
neit	O	O	O	O	O
nao	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
feest	O	O	O	O	O
van	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
achtentwintigsten	O	O	O	O	O
in	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
stad	O	O	O	O	O
?	O	O	O	O	O
Omdat	O	O	O	O	O
’k	O	O	O	O	O
neit	O	O	O	O	O
best	O	O	O	O	O
in	O	O	O	O	O
order	O	O	O	O	O
was	O	O	O	O	O
vaoder	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
zegt	O	O	O	O	O
Trudao	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
;	O	O	O	O	O
maor	O	O	O	O	O
ze	O	O	O	O	O
stuttert	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
lippen	O	O	O	O	O
trillen	O	O	O	O	O
heur	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
ze	O	O	O	O	O
stekt	O	O	O	O	O
zōk	O	O	O	O	O
mit	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
stopnâll’	O	O	O	O	O
in	O	O	O	O	O
de	O	O	O	O	O
hand	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
’t	O	O	O	O	O
bloud	O	O	O	O	O
lopt	O	O	O	O	O
d’r	O	O	O	O	O
oet	O	O	O	O	O
;	O	O	O	O	O
maor	O	O	O	O	O
ze	O	O	O	O	O
vuilt	O	O	O	O	O
of	O	O	O	O	O
zōgt	O	O	O	O	O
d’r	O	O	O	O	O
niks	O	O	O	O	O
van	O	O	O	O	O
.	O	O	O	O	O
Robbers	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
maokt	O	O	O	O	O
oet	O	O	O	O	O
heur	O	O	O	O	O
verlegenhaid	O	O	O	O	O
op	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dat	O	O	O	O	O
ze	O	O	O	O	O
hōm	O	O	O	O	O
verlōgt	O	O	O	O	O
en	O	O	O	O	O
begunt	O	O	O	O	O
in	O	O	O	O	O
raozende	O	O	O	O	O
drift	O	O	O	O	O
oet	O	O	O	O	O
te	O	O	O	O	O
vaoren	O	O	O	O	O
:	O	O	O	O	O
Neit	O	O	O	O	O
best	O	O	O	O	O
in	O	O	O	O	O
order	O	O	O	O	O
?	O	O	O	O	O
jah	O	O	O	O	O
!	O	O	O	O	O
omdast	O	O	O	O	O
die	O	O	O	O	O
zeik	O	O	O	O	O
tiert	O	O	O	O	O
hest	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
omdast	O	O	O	O	O
ofspraok	O	O	O	O	O
harst	O	O	O	O	O
mit	O	O	O	O	O
dei	O	O	O	O	O
kaoljaoger	O	O	O	O	O
!	O	O	O	O	O
omdast	O	O	O	O	O
wel	O	O	O	O	O
weist	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dat	O	O	O	O	O
’k	O	O	O	O	O
dei	O	O	O	O	O
vent	O	O	O	O	O
hier	O	O	O	O	O
neit	O	O	O	O	O
weiten	O	O	O	O	O
wil	O	O	O	O	O
!	O	O	O	O	O
Schaom	O	O	O	O	O
die	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
mie	O	O	O	O	O
zoo	O	O	O	O	O
te	O	O	O	O	O
verleigen	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
die	O	O	O	O	O
mit	O	O	O	O	O
zoo	O	O	O	O	O
’n	O	O	O	O	O
lappert	O	O	O	O	O
of	O	O	O	O	O
te	O	O	O	O	O
geven	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
mie	O	O	O	O	O
wies	O	O	O	O	O
te	O	O	O	O	O
maoken	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dast	O	O	O	O	O
nao	O	O	O	O	O
doomnie’s	O	O	O	O	O
Lize	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER	B-PER
gaist	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
om	O	O	O	O	O
daor	O	O	O	O	O
maor	O	O	O	O	O
bie	O	O	O	O	O
dei	O	O	O	O	O
kaole	O	O	O	O	O
vent	O	O	O	O	O
te	O	O	O	O	O
komen	O	O	O	O	O
,	O	O	O	O	O
dei	O	O	O	O	O
neit	O	O	O	O	O
vörrels	O	O	O	O	O
dien	O	O	O	O	O
liek	O	O	O	O	O
is	O	O	O	O	O
!	O	O	O	O	O
